{
    "Unix-intro":[
        {
            "id" : 1,
            "question": "what is Unix? ",
            "ans": " It is an operating system which is a special software that controls the hardware of a computer system"
        },

        {
            "id": 2,
            "question": "Is Unix and Linux same? ",
            "ans": "No, they are not. Linux is derived from Unix. Linux is used with GNU (an OS) which stands for GNU is Not Unix"
        },
        {
            "id": 3,
            "question": "Why use UNIX? ",
            "ans": "it provides modularity, portability, simplicity, adapility, highly secured, and Linux os is everywhere! "
        },
        {
            "id": 4,
            "question": "What is the goal of Unix? ",
            "ans": "Multi-processes, Multi-users, Multi-tasking"
        },
        {
            "id": 5,
            "question": "What are the different components in the unix architecture starting from the lowest level (middle)? ",
            "ans": "Hardware, Kernel, Shell, Application"
        }
    ],

    "File-management":[
        {
            "id" : 6,
            "question": "ls",
            "ans": "lists all “visible” files in current directory"
        },

        {
            "id": 7,
            "question": "ls -la",
            "ans": "Lists all files in current directory and presents them in a long list format."
        },

        {
            "id" : 8,
            "question": "cp <filename1> <filename2>",
            "ans": "copy existing filename1 into new filename2."
        },

        {
            "id" : 9,
            "question": "cp -r <dir1> <dir2>",
            "ans": "“copy”, recursively. copy existing contents of directory1 into directory2."
        },

        {
            "id" : 10,
            "question": "rm <filename1> <filename2>",
            "ans": "remove filename1 and filename2. * Not reversible!" 
        },

        {
            "id" : 11,
            "question": "rm -r <directory1>'",
            "ans": "remove recursively directory1 and all its contents. * Not reversible!" 
        },
        
        {
            "id" : 12,
            "question": "mv <file1> <directory1>",
            "ans": " move file1 into directory1. * Not reversible!" 
        },

        {
            "id" : 13,
            "question": "cat <filename>",
            "ans": "“catalogue”. Display file contents."
        },

        {
            "id" : 14,
            "question":  "cat <file1> > <file2>",
            "ans": "Overwite the contents of file2 with the contents of file1."
        },

        {
            "id" : 15,
            "question": "cat <file1> >> <file2>",
            "ans": " Write the contents of file1 to the end of file2."
        },
        {
            "id" : 16,
            "question": "cat <file1> >> <file2>",
            "ans": " Write the contents of file1 to the end of file2."
        },
        {
            "id" : 17,
            "question": "cat *.txt",
            "ans": " Show the content of all text files present in the folder."
        },
        {
            "id" : 18,
            "question": "What is tar commands?",
            "ans": "stands for tape archive, to create archive or extract archive files"
        },
        {
            "id" : 19,
            "question": "tar -cvf dir_1.tar dir_1",
            "ans": " To bundle all the content of dir_1 into a single file called dir_1.tar"
        },
        {
            "id" : 20,
            "question": "tar xvf file.tar",
            "ans": " To extract files for archive file"
        },
        {
            "id" : 21,
            "question": "touch",
            "ans": "display content, one screen at the time"
        },
        {
            "id" : 22,
            "question": "more",
            "ans": "display content, one screen at the time"
        }
    ],

    "Environment":[
        {
            "id" : 23,
            "question": "man",
            "ans": "stand for manual, give you more information about the command"
        },

        {
            "id" : 24,
            "question": "uname",
            "ans": "display information about the system"
        },

        {
            "id" : 25,
            "question": "whoami",
            "ans": "show current active user"
        },

        {
            "id" : 26,
            "question": "who",
            "ans": "gives information on current logged in users. It tells of the login name and time."
        },

        {
            "id" : 27,
            "question": "su",
            "ans": "stand for subtitute user ( often mistaken as super use)"
        },

        {
            "id" : 28,
            "question": "passwd",
            "ans": "this command changes your password"
        },

        {
            "id" : 29,
            "question": "whereis",
            "ans": "this command is used to find where a command exists"
        },

        {
            "id" : 30,
            "question": "whatis",
            "ans": "quickly see an single line description on what a command does"
        },

        {
            "id" : 31,
            "question": "ps",
            "ans": "display all the current processes owned by the current user"
        },
        
        {
            "id" : 32,
            "question": "ctrl-c",
            "ans": "terminate a process"
        },

        {
            "id" : 33,
            "question": "ctrl-d",
            "ans": "terminate an external preocess"
        },

        {
            "id" : 34,
            "question": "ctrl-z",
            "ans": "suspends a job"
        },

        {
            "id" : 35,
            "question": "bg",
            "ans": "resume the suspended jobs in the background"
        },

        {
            "id" : 36,
            "question": "fg",
            "ans": "resume the suspended jobs in the foreground"
        },

        {
            "id" : 37,
            "question": "top",
            "ans": "gives you real time resource usage by job for the machine. Terminates with ctrl-c"
        },  
        {
            "id" : 38,
            "question": "ssh",
            "ans": "a protocol that a secure connection between two hosts (remote) over an insecure network"
        },
        {
            "id" : 39,
            "question": "scp",
            "ans": "a protocol that copies a file from a local computer onto a remote host"
        },
        {
            "id" : 40,
            "question": "ifconfig",
            "ans": "view or configure a network."
        },
        {
            "id" : 41,
            "question": "ping",
            "ans": "see if a server is available and there is a connection between two nodes"
        },
        {
            "id" : 42,
            "question": "g++",
            "ans": "used in c++ development for preprocessing, compiling, assembling, and linking source code to create an executable"
        },
        {
            "id" : 43,
            "question": "kill",
            "ans": "terminate specific processes"
        },
        {
            "id" : 44,
            "question": "&",
            "ans": "see if a server is available and there is a connection between two nodes"
        },
        {
            "id" : 45,
            "question": "env",
            "ans": "displays all of the environment variables"
        }

        
    ],

    "Directory Management":[
        {
            "id" : 46,
            "question": "du -sh ~",
            "ans": "tells the disk usage for your home directory."
        },
        {
            "id" : 47,
            "question": "pwd",
            "ans": "displaying what directory you are currently in"
        },
        {
            "id" : 48,
            "question": "cd",
            "ans": "traversing through the directory structure"
        },
        {
            "id" : 49,
            "question": "mkdir",
            "ans": "creates a seperate empty directory"
        },
        {
            "id" : 50,
            "question": "rmdir",
            "ans": "remove a directory"
        },
        {
            "id" : 51,
            "question": "mv",
            "ans": "used to rename or move a directory"
        },
        {
            "id" : 52,
            "question": "absolute",
            "ans": "starts form the root directory and includes all subsequent directories"
        },
        {
            "id" : 53,
            "question": "relative path",
            "ans": "starts from the current directory continues down the branches of the tree"
        }
    ]
}

